Finding aid to the Wead family papers SSC.MS.00171
Sophia Smith Collection
Wead family papers
1860-1936
Sophia Smith Collection
Wead family
SSC.MS.00171
.25 linear feet (1 container)
Mary Wead was a U.S. Sanitary Commission volunteer during the Civil War and Eunice Wead was a Smith College librarian in the early 20th century. The Wead Family papers consist primarily of correspondence to and from Mary Wead in the course of her work with the U.S. Sanitary Commission during the Civil War. Correspondents with both Mary and Eunice Wead include Louisa Lee Schuyler, leader in 19th century welfare work; author Amy Lowell; and Letitia Campbell of the Freedman's Union Commission. There is a small amount of correspondence to other Wead family members.
Biographical / Historical
Mary K. Wead (1812-1896) worked for the United States Sanitary Commission (Woman's Central Association of Relief) during the Civil War, and during the 1880s was an inspector for the New York State Charities Association for Franklin County. She married Samuel Wead. For additional biographical information, see pages 12-14 in "The Wead Family & Its Relations to Malone" in Box 1 Folder 1a.
Eunice Wead (1881-1969), (Mary's granddaughter?), graduated from Smith College in 1902, and received her Masters degree from the University of Michigan in 1927. She was a librarian at Smith College from 1906 to 1911; Curator of Rare Books from 1917 to 1924; and was Associate Professor of Library Science at the University of Michigan from 1926-1944.
Scope and Contents
The Wead Family papers consist primarily of correspondence to and from Mary Wead in the course of her work with the U.S. Sanitary Commission during the Civil War. There are also bills received for materials she purchased for the Union Army. Correspondents with both Mary and Eunice Wead include Louisa Lee Schuyler, leader in 19th century welfare work; author Amy Lowell; and Letitia Campbell of the Freedman's Union Commission. There is a small amount of correspondence to other Wead family members (circa 1911-36).
Related Material
Additional material related to Eunice Wead is located in the Smith College Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Eunice Wead donated her family papers to the Sophia Smith Collection circa 1944.
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Women; correspondence; Financial records; Lowell, Amy, 1874-1925--Correspondence; Schuyler, Louisa Lee, 1837-1926--Correspondence; Wead, Mary, 1812-1896; Wead, Mary Eunice; American Freedman's Union Commission--History--Sources; National Freedmen's Relief Association--History--Sources; Woman's Central Association of Relief--History--Sources; State Charities Aid Association (New York)--History--Sources; United States Sanitary Commission--History--Sources; unknown; Wead, Eunice; Wead family
- Contents: list and index (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical: Leslie C. Wead, "The Wead Family and its Relation to Malone [N.Y.]", 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- Correspondence
  - Mary Wead
    - Campbell, Laetitia, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Collins, Ellen, 1862-78 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Curtis, Mary, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - D'Orenienlx, Laura, 1863-64 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Freedman's Union Commission, 1865-66 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Griffin, Christine Kean, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Parsons, Lizzie, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Piere, R., 1867 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sampson, E. A., 1866-67 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Post, Angelina, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Schuyler, Louisa Lee, 1864; 1865; 1881 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Stuart, George H., 1864 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Van Amringe, Susan M., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Whitney, Maria, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Sinclaire, Myra, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Eunice Wead
    - Woolson, G.H., 1906 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lowell, Amy, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Pilcher, Sophia (Suffrage, Mrs. Simpson, abdication of Edward VIII - 1936), 1911; 1913 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Mary Wead--Miscellaneous
  - Bills for items purchased for Union Army, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - State Charities Aid Association Forms, 1881-82 (Box 1, Folder 21)